听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我们接下来学习广播协议
Next, we are going to look at broadcast protocols.
从逻辑时间直接调到了具体协议 这似乎有些突然
This might seem like a bit of a sudden jump from logical time.
但我们随后就会看到 广播协议和逻辑时间实际上有很强的关联性
But actually, as we will see in a moment, there's a strong connection between the two.
广播协议扩展了我们在分布式系统中
So, broadcast protocols generalize the type of network communication
支持的网络通信类型
that we can do in a distributed system.
之前 我们主要考察的是点对点通信
So, so far, we've been considering point-to-point communication
一个发送方通过网络将消息发送给一个接收方
where one sender sends a message to one recipient over the network.
消息可能会被送达 也可能未被送达
The message may or may not arrive,
但这仍然是两个节点之间的点对点通信
but it's still one-to-one communication between two nodes.
在广播或组播通信中 我们将通信类型扩展到节点群组
In broadcast or multicast communication, we generalize this to a group of nodes
一个节点可以同时向群组中的所有其他节点发送一条消息
so that one node may send a message to all of the nodes in the group at the same time.
出于本课程的教学目的 我们总会假设
Now, for the purpose of this course, we're mostly going to assume that
群组中包含的节点集合是固定的、预先已知的
the set of nodes in the group is fixed and known in advance.
但一般来说 实际应用的系统中
But in general, you may well, of course, have a system
节点可以动态加入或离开 或者被管理员添加或移除
in which nodes can join and leave or be added or removed by an administrator.
真实协议显然需要处理这类情况
And that is certainly something that real protocols need to deal with.
我们特别希望广播协议满足容错性
So, one particular thing that we want of a broadcast protocol is fault tolerance.
也就是说 当群组中的一个节点出现故障时
And this means that, say, one of the nodes in the group is faulty,
剩余的所有节点
all of the remaining nodes
应该仍然可以继续广播和传递消息
should still be able to continue broadcasting and delivering messages as before.
我们不希望单节点故障就会让整个系统逐渐中止
So, we don't want a single faulty node to make the entire system grind to a halt.
有几种不同的广播或组播实现方式
There are a couple of different implementations of broadcast or multicast.
在计算机网络中 大家可能遇到过一种广播机制
One that you might have come across in the context of computer networking is that
一些局域网实际上在硬件层支持广播或组播
some local area networks support broadcast or multicast at the hardware level actually.
这在局域网中非常有用
And this is quite useful on local area networks.
一般来说 局域网的组播机制无法在公开互联网上工作
Generally, that kind of multicast does not work over the public Internet.
我们在本课程中
And so, what we will consider in this course
考虑的是更一般形式的广播或组播
is more general form of multicast or broadcast
我们假设
where we assume that
基础网络仅提供点对点消息传输机制 即仅提供单播机制
the underlying network only provides point-to-point messaging as in unicast,
我们要在单播机制上构建广播协议
and we are going to build broadcast protocols on top of that.
基础网络只允许我们
So, the underlying network just allows us to
从一个节点向另一个节点发送一条消息
send a message from one node to one other node,
在此基础上 我们可以将广播协议构建成一个抽象方法
but on top of that, we can build broadcast as an abstraction
允许更高层协议调用广播协议
that we can then use for higher-level protocols.
如果你还记得课程2中有关系统模型的讨论
So, if you think back to the discussion of system models in lecture 2,
我们讲解了公平丢包链路和可靠链路的差异
we have the distinction between fair-loss links and reliable links.
当然了 大多数网络链路都是公平丢包链路
And of course, most network links are fair-loss,
但你可以通过消息重传使公平丢包链路变为可靠链路
but you can make them reliable by re-transmitting messages.
广播协议也有相同的链路差异
Exactly the same distinction happens in broadcast protocols,
唯一的区别是 如果网络可能丢失消息
except here that a network that might lose message,
我们一般称对应的广播机制为尽力广播
we call best-effort broadcast typically.
尽力广播的意思是 一个节点尝试向所有其他节点发送消息
Best-effort broadcast just means one node tries to send message to all the other nodes,
但消息可能会被传达 也可能不会被传达
but it may or may not arrive.
尤其是当发送方崩溃时
Especially if the sender crashes, for example,
消息可能无法传达到所有其他的节点
the message might not reach all of the other nodes.
我们可以让其变成可靠的 同样需要依赖丢失消息重传机制
Or, we can make it reliable, which again relies on re-transmitting lost messages.
与系统模型中的介绍类似
Like in the context of system models,
我们假设系统不满足同步系统模型
we are going to assume not a synchronous system model,
我们假设异步或部分同步系统模型
but an asynchronous or partially asynchronous system model,
这意味着我们不为消息延迟设置任何上界
which means that we're not going to assume any upper bound on message latency.
在可靠广播协议中
So, in a reliable broadcast protocol,
我们可以说消息最终一定能传输成功
we can say that the message will eventually go get through,
但我们不会承诺
but we're not making any promises about
消息会花费多长的时间才会传输成功
how long it might take until the message might get through.
这就是广播的相关背景知识了
OK, so, that's the background on broadcast.
在讲解具体细节之前 我需要介绍一些术语
I should introduce a little bit of terminology before I get into the details.
在点对点网络链路中
And that is, in the context of point-to-point network links,
我们讨论了通过网络发送和接收消息
we have talked about sending and receiving messages over the network,
在广播协议中
whereas in the context of broadcast protocols,
与点对点网络链路相对应 我们讨论的是广播并传递一条消息
we talk about broadcasting a message and then delivering it as the counterpart.
实际发生的情况是
So, what happens is
一个节点的应用希望向整个群组广播一条消息
the application on one node wants to broadcast a message to the entire group.
我们称这个动作为广播
We call this action a broadcast.
随后 底层广播算法
And then, the underlying broadcast algorithm
会通过网络发送或接收多条消息
may send or receive multiple messages over the network,
这些消息是通过点对点网络发送或接收的
and these are then point-to-point messages that are sent or received.
其他节点可能会收到相应的消息
And on some other node, those messages might be received.
广播算法会接收这些消息
They get again picked up by the broadcast algorithm.
随后 广播算法会在某个时间点将消息传递给应用
And the broadcast algorithm at some point then delivers the message to the application.
这里 传递与广播是相互对应的
So, here the delivery is the counterpart to the broadcast.
这里的一个细节点是
And one detail that happens here is that
当广播算法收到消息时
when the broadcast algorithm receives a message,
广播算法可能不会立刻将消息传递给应用
it might not immediately deliver that to the application.
广播算法可能会等待一段时间 直到准备好传递消息
It may actually have to wait for a little bit before that message is ready to be delivered,
因为我们想要保证消息按照特定的顺序传递给应用
because we want to ensure that the messages are delivered in a certain order.
这些就是用到的术语了
So, this is just the terminology.
我们现在将会介绍几种不同的抽象广播方法
We are now going to look at a couple of different broadcast abstractions.
我后面会分别独立地详细介绍这些广播方法
And I'm going to talk about each of these individually.
因此 我现在不会讲解太多的具体细节
So, I won't go into too much detail right now.
这里的一个关键点是 这些协议都是可靠广播
The point here is that these are all forms of reliable broadcasts.
我们要假设存在一个重传机制
So, we're assuming we have a mechanism for re-transmission,
可以保证所有的消息最终都会被成功传输
which ensures that all of the messages eventually get through.
现在 我们想根据消息传递的顺序
Now, we want to distinguish different types of broadcasts
来区分不同类型的广播协议
based on the order in which messages get delivered.
我们要介绍的第一个协议是FIFO（先进先出）广播
And so, the first one that we're going to look at is FIFO broadcast.
FIFO广播的消息传递顺序是
And in FIFO broadcast, the ordering property is that
如果两个消息是由同一个节点广播的
if two messages are broadcast by the same node,
则所有节点会按照相同的广播顺序传递这些消息
then all nodes will deliver those messages in the same order as they were broadcast.
对于单个特定节点的广播消息 消息传递时会保证顺序一致
So, for any messages broadcast from one particular node, they remain in order,
但对于两个不同节点的广播消息
but for any messages broadcast by two different nodes,
协议不会保证传递顺序与发送顺序一致
there's no guarantee about the order in which they might arrive.
我们通过一个具体的例子来了解这个协议的执行过程
So, let's look at an example of what this actually looks like.
这里我们同样有三个节点A、B和C
So, here we have again three nodes A, B and C.
A想要在群组中广播消息m_1
A wants to broadcast message m_1 to the group.
因此 A通过网络将消息发送给C和B
And so, it sends that message over the network to C and to B.
请注意 A也给自己发送了这条消息
And notice also that A sends the message to itself,
我们用这个小的回环箭头表示自己给自己发送消息
which is here denoted by this little loopback arrow.
看起来似乎没必要这样做
Now, this might seem unnecessary,
为什么需要把一个消息传回给自己呢
because why do you need to deliver a message back to yourself,
此消息的发送方已经知道要发送的消息是什么了
because the sender of the message already knows what message is sent,
没必要再接收一次这条消息
it doesn't need to receive it again.
我们后续讨论全序关系广播时
The reason why a node delivers a message to itself
节点向自己传递一条消息的原因就变得很显然了
will become apparent when we talk about total order broadcast shortly.
现在 我们仅把这看成是一个小怪癖
So, for now just assume this as a little quirk that
假设广播协议保证总会让发送方给自己也传递一条广播消息
the guarantee of the broadcast protocol is also always that it delivers a message to itself.
当m_1完成消息传递后
Then, after m_1 has been delivered,
节点B决定向群组广播消息m_2
node B decides that it wants to broadcast message m_2 to the group.
因此 B通过网络向A和C发送m_2
And so, it sends m_2 over the network to A and C,
B也给自己传递m_2
and it also delivers m_2 to itself.
最后 节点A想要广播消息m_3
And then, finally, node A wants to broadcast message m_3.
同样地 A通过网络向B和C发送m_3
So, again, it sends that message over the network to B and C,
A也给自己传递m_3
and it delivers m_3 to itself.
这就是FIFO广播
OK, so, this is FIFO broadcast.
正如我前面所说 我们要求FIFO广播满足的性质是
So, what we require for FIFO broadcast, as I said just now, is that
因为m_1和m_3都是由相同的节点A广播的
because m_1 and m_3 are both broadcast by the same node A,
我们要求所有节点在传递m_3之前先传递m_1
we require that all nodes deliver m_1 before they deliver m_3.
我们可以检查一下 事实的确如此
And we can check that this is the case here.
这里A传递m_1 再传递m_3
A delivers m_1 here, and then delivers m_3, OK?
B传递m_1 再传递m_3
B delivers m_1, then delivers m_3.
C也先传递m_1 再传递m_3
And C also delivers m_1, and then delivers m_3.
很好 所有节点都按照正确的顺序传递消息
OK, all fine. All of the nodes delivered these messages in the right order.
FIFO广播下
Now, there are actually several possible orders
有多种合理的消息传递顺序
that would be valid here under FIFO broadcast.
特别地 由B发送的消息m_2
In particular, the message m_2 that is sent by B,
可以把它的传递顺序放在A消息的任意位置上
that can be ordered arbitrarily with respect to A's messages,
因为我们不保证不同节点消息的传递顺序
because we are not making any guarantees about ordering across different nodes,
而m_2是由B发送的
and m_2 was sent by B,
这意味着m_2的传递顺序
so, this means that it's OK for m_2 to be delivered
可以在m_1和m_3之前、之间、或者之后
before m_1 and m_3, or in between the two, or after the two.
这些传递顺序都是合理的
And all of those are fine.
举例来说 我们可以考虑这两个不同的执行效果
And, so here, for example, we can consider these two different executions,
这两个执行效果中 C传递消息的顺序有所不同
in which the messages are delivered by C in a different order.
在这个情况下 C先传递m_1、再传递m_2、再传递m_3
So, in this case, here m_1 is delivered first, then m_2, then m_3.
在这个情况下 C先传递m_2、再传递m_1、再传递m_3
In this case, m_2 is delivered first, then m_1, then m_3.
在FIFO广播下 这两种消息传递顺序都是合理的
And both of these orders are valid under FIFO broadcast.
即使在这种情况下 你认为m_2和m_1有因果关系
Even though, in this case, here for example, the message m_2,
消息m_2应该发生在消息m_1之后
you would say that happened after m_1 in a causal sense,
但FIFO广播不会保证先传递m_1、再传递m_2
but still FIFO broadcast makes no guarantees about delivering m_2 after m_1.
如果你确实希望传递顺序满足因果关系 你就需要因果关系广播了
If you do want that kind of ordering property, you need causal broadcast.
因果关系广播保证消息按照因果顺序传递
So, causal broadcast ensures that messages are delivered in causal order.
这意味着如果广播一条消息
That means that if the broadcasting of one message
在广播另一条消息之前发生
happened before the broadcasting of another,
也就是说两次广播满足此前发生关系
in the sense that happens-before relation,
那么这些消息也必须按照这个顺序传递
then those messages must be delivered in that order
传递顺序要满足此前发生关系
that matches that happens-before relation.
这就是这里演示的传递顺序
And that's what we have here.
首先 m_1由A广播
So, first of all, m_1 is broadcast by A,
B和C收到了消息 B传递了此消息
and it's received by B and C, and it's delivered by B here.
随后 在B传递m_1之后想广播m_2
And then, after B has delivered m_1, B wants to broadcast m_2.
这里的m_2可能与m_1有因果依赖关系
And so, here m_2 may have a causal dependency on m_1.
因此 我们要求所有的节点必须先传递m_1、再传递m_2
And therefore, we require that all of the nodes must deliver m_1 first and m_2 second.
接下来 节点A可能想广播消息m_3
Next, the node A might broadcast a message m_3.
A同样通过网络向其他两个节点发送此消息
Again, it sends that over the network to the other two nodes,
且A向自己传递了此消息
and it delivers the message to itself.
在这种情况下
And in this case,
注意到m_2的广播与m_3的广播是并发的
notice that the broadcast of m_2 is concurrent with the broadcast of m_3,
因为A是在m_3广播之后才传递的m_2
because on A, m_2 is delivered after m_3 is broadcast,
而B是在m_2广播之后才传递的m_3
and on B, m_3 is delivered after m_2 is broadcast.
因此 这两条消息之间没有依赖关系
So, these two messages do not depend on each other.
在这种情况下 我们要求的是
So, in this case, here what we require is that
任意存在因果依赖关系的消息必须按照因果顺序传递
any messages that have a causal dependency are delivered in causal order.
因此 在这种情况下 m_1和m_2存在因果依赖关系
And so, in this case, here we have a causal dependency between m_1 and m_2,
且m_1和m_3存在因果依赖关系
and we have a causal dependency between m_1 and m_3,
因为m_1和m_3是由相同的节点A所广播的
because m_1 and m_3 were broadcast by the same node A.
但m_2和m_3不存在因果依赖关系
But there's no causal dependency between m_2 and m_3.
因此 这意味着可以按任意一种顺序传递m_2和m_3
And so, this means m_2 and m_3 can be delivered in either order,
C仍然有两种不同的消息传递顺序
which means that here again, we have two different orders of delivery for C,
这两种消息传递顺序对于因果关系广播来说都是合理的
and both of these are OK under causal broadcast.
在这种情况下 C首先传递m_1、再传递m_3、再传递m_2
So, here, in this case, we have C first delivering m_1, then m_3, then m_2.
在这种情况下 C首先传递m_1、再传递m_2、再传递m_3
In this case, here we have C first delivering m_1, then m_2, then m_3.
这两种传递顺序都是合理的
And these are both valid orders.
我们可以交换m_2和m_3的传递顺序
We can swap around the delivery order of m_2 and m_3.
注意到 这里A先传递m_1、再传递m_3、再传递m_2
Now, notice here, for example, that A delivers first delivers m_1, then m_3, then m_2,
而B先传递m_1、再传递m_2、再传递m_3
whereas B delivers first m_1, then m_2, then m_3.
这两种都是合理的因果顺序 但这两种顺序不相同
So, both of these orders are valid causal orders, but they are not the same.
有些情况下 我们实际上要求
And in some cases, we actually want to require that
所有节点按照相同的顺序传递消息
all of the nodes deliver messages in the same order.
如果我们希望满足这一要求 我们就需要转向所谓的全序关系广播了
And if that is what we want, we need to move to what is called total order broadcast.
全序关系广播
So, total order broadcast
将系统中的所有广播消息按照全序关系排列
puts all of the messages that are broadcast in the system into a total order.
这意味着消息的传递顺序总是清晰的
That means it's always clear which one came first.
全序关系广播保证所有节点按照相同的顺序传递消息
And it ensures that all of the nodes deliver messages in that same order.
所有节点将会一起协商好
So, there's agreement between all of the nodes on the order
所需的消息传递顺序
in which the messages should be delivered.
举例来说 在这个例子中 我们从A广播m_1开始
So, in this example, again, we start with m_1 broadcast by A,
随后 我们让B在m_1之后广播m_2
then we have m_2 broadcast by B, which happens after m_1,
最后 我们让A广播消息m_3
and finally, we have a message m_3 that is broadcast by A again.
在这种情况 我们需要在某个地方
Now, in this case, something somewhere
决定这些消息的传递顺序
has to decide on the order in which these will be delivered.
假定决定好的顺序是
Let's say that the order that was decided is to
先传递m_1、再传递m_2、再传递m_3
deliver first m_1, then m_2, then m_3, OK?
我们以C为例 看看会发生什么
And so, we can see on C, for example, that's what happened.
C先传递m_1、再传递m_2、再传递m_3
C first delivers m_1, then it delivers m_2, then it delivers m_3.
C按照正确的顺序传递消息
So, C is delivering them in the correct order.
我们来看看B
Let's look at B.
这里B先传递m_1、再给自己传递m_2、再传递m_3
Here B first delivers m_1, then it delivers m_2 to itself, then it delivers m_3, OK?
因此 B也按照正确的顺序传递消息
So, B also delivers the messages in the correct order.
来看看节点A
Let's look at node A here.
A先给自己传递m_1
Node A first delivers m_1 to itself,
接下来 A广播m_3 但稍等下 此时A不能给自己传递m_3
then it broadcasts m_3, but wait, it's not allowed to deliver m_3 to itself yet,
因为决定好的顺序要求先传递m_2、再传递m_3
because the order that was decided is that m_2 must be delivered before m_3.
因此 节点A不能立刻给自己传递m_3
So, therefore, node A cannot immediately deliver m_3 to itself.
A需要先等待m_2的到来并传递m_2
Instead, it has to wait first for m_2 to arrive and m_2 to be delivered by A,
随后A才能给自己传递m_3
and only then is A allowed to deliver m_3 to itself.
这就是自我传递顺序变得非常有趣、非常关键的地方
So, this is now where this delivery-to-self becomes very interesting and crucial,
你可以看到 当要给自己传递消息时
because you can see that sometimes there has to be this delay
节点在这种情况下必须引入一些延迟
if a node wants to deliver a message to itself.
这里的m_1、m_2、m_3是一种可能的消息传递顺序
Now here, m_1, m_2, then m_3 is one possible order of delivering these messages.
我们也可以决定使用不同的消息传递顺序
It could also be that we decide on a different order.
另一个合理的消息传递顺序可能是m_1、m_3、m_2
So, a different valid order might be for the delivery order to be m_1, m_3, m_2.
我们只要求所有节点按照相同的顺序传递消息
And that is also fine, as long as all of the nodes deliver the messages in that same order.
这里 我们从C开始
And so, here again, we have start with C.
C先传递m_1、再传递m_3、再传递m_2
So, C first delivers m_1, then m_3, then m_2.
注意 这里可能出现的情况是
Notice here that it's possible that
C在收到m_3之前 先通过网络收到了m_2
C receives m_2 over the network before it receives m_3,
此时 C必须等待m_3的到来 延迟传递m_2
in which case, C will have to delay the delivery of m_2 until after m_3 has arrived.
在广播算法中 这被称为保留广播
So here, this is called a holdback in the broadcast algorithm.
如果消息还没有准备好传递 通常需要先保留消息
It's often necessary for a message to be held back if it's not yet ready to be delivered,
因为我们需要先等待其他消息的到来
because we're waiting for some other message to arrive first.
C就遇到了这种情况
And that has happened here in the case of C.
在节点B中 为了让传递顺序为m_1、m_3、m_2
In the node B, for the delivery order to be m_1, m_3, m_2,
我们首先传递m_1 再广播m_2
well, first, we deliver m_1, then we broadcast m_2,
但我们不能立刻让B给自己传递m_2
but we can't immediately deliver m_2 to ourselves.
我们需要先等待m_3传递完毕
We have to first wait for m_3 to be delivered.
随后 我们才能让B传递m_2
And then, we're allowed to deliver m_2 to ourselves at B.
节点A的情况比较简单
And on node A, things are simpler now.
首先 我们让A给自己传递m_1 随后我们让A给自己传递m_3
So, first, we deliver m_1 to ourselves, then we deliver m_3 to ourselves,
最后 m_2通过网络到达A 我们让A给自己传递m_2
and finally, m_2 arrives over the network, and we deliver m_2 to ourselves.
以上两种情况都是合理的全序关系广播执行过程
So, both of these here are valid executions of total order broadcasts.
重要的是 无论我们按照何种顺序传递消息
The crucial thing is just that whatever order the messages get delivered in,
所有节点的消息传递顺序必须都相同
that order has to be the same for all of the nodes.
最后 我们还有所谓的FIFO全序关系广播
Finally, there's something called FIFO-total order broadcast,
就是把全序关系广播与FIFO顺序组合在一起
which just combines total order broadcast with FIFO ordering.
意思是所有节点必须按照相同的顺序传递消息
So, that means all the nodes have to deliver messages in the same order,
同时
and also,
相同节点发送的消息必须按照发送顺序传递
messages sent by the same node have to be the delivered in the order they were sent.
可以证明 FIFO全序关系广播严格强于因果关系广播
And it turns out that FIFO-total order broadcast is strictly stronger than causal broadcast.
每次执行FIFO全序关系广播
So, every execution of FIFO-total order broadcast
也必须满足因果关系广播的要求
also meets the requirement of causal broadcast,
每次执行因果关系广播也必须满足FIFO广播的要求
and every execution of causal broadcast also meets the requirement of FIFO broadcast.
每次执行FIFO广播也必须满足可靠广播的要求 以此类推
Every FIFO broadcast meets the requirement of reliable broadcast, and so on.
本节课的讲义中有一个练习
So, there's actually an exercise in the lecture notes for this lecture
就是要求你证明广播模型之间的这一相互关系
that asks you to prove some of these relationships between the broadcast models.
下一小节 我们将学习
In the next section, we will then look at
如何实现这些广播算法
how to actually implement some of these broadcast algorithms.